<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>Enketo Blog</title>
	<link type="application/atom+xml" href="http://blog.enketo.org/feed/" rel="self" />
	<link href="http://blog.enketo.org"/>
	<updated>2013-05-17T10:14:47-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://blog.enketo.org</id>
	<author>
	  <name>Martijn van de Rijdt</name>
	</author>
	<rights>Copyright (c) 2010-2013 Martijn van de Rijdt</rights>

	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Presentation on Enketo for Humanitarian Nomad 2013</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/nomad-presention-2013//" />
	  <updated>2013-05-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/nomad-presention-2013//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to remotely present Enketo Smart Paper during the &lt;a href=&quot;http://humanitarian-nomad.org/&quot;&gt;Humanitarian Nomad&lt;/a&gt; workshop in Paris yesterday. A pretty cool milestone because enketo was developed specifically for humanitarian aid workers and is now robust enough to be widely deployed in the field. See the slides below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;




&lt;iframe style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1vW75DmQrbK91l8AVrKYx2UR7b7EQgqcEOfSfQhF9iWY/embed?start=false&amp;loop=false&amp;delayms=3000&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;




&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I plan to do a lot more promotion for Enketo Smart Paper in the future and hope I can be present in person at the next &lt;a href=&quot;http://humanitarian-nomad.org&quot;&gt;Humanitarian Nomad&lt;/a&gt; event. Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.immap.org/&quot;&gt;iMMAP&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://cartong.org/&quot;&gt;CartONG&lt;/a&gt; for leading this initiative and helping organisations find the right tool for the job with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://humanitarian-nomad.org/online-selection-tool/&quot;&gt;online selection tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Smart Paper</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-branding//" />
	  <updated>2013-05-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-branding//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you have visited enketo.org recently you will have noticed the gorgeous new logo and front page, and the new branding as Enketo Smart Paper. I love the new look but can take no credit for it. It was the result of an in-depth analysis of enketo by my colleagues, &lt;a href=&quot;http://modi.mech.columbia.edu/&quot;&gt;Modilab&lt;/a&gt;'s senior designer Roger Wong and ICT Director Matt Berg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2013/05/enketo_smart_paper_300x240.png&quot; alt=&quot;enketo logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As somebody who has always been very interested in graphic design and web design, I have been very impressed (and a little envious) with both the process and the end result of this design challenge. I'm hoping that witnessing this process in enketo and other projects will eventually start to rub off on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why Smart Paper?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enketo forms are as familiar and easy to use as paper, but they're smart. Sections magically appear when you progress through a form based on previous answers. Data quality can be enforced by smart validation logic designed into a form. Moreover, one of the core features of enketo is to automatically generate a print-friendly version of each form for old-fashioned collection by paper and pen. So there is no need to maintain different versions of the same form!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enketo.org&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The branding and design work is one of the final phases of the forthcoming launch of enketo.org. Another was the renaming of Aid Web Solutions to Enketo LLC. There is still work to be done and decisions to be made, but we're getting close. I'll write a post about this in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Enketo starts to fly</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-performance//" />
	  <updated>2013-03-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-performance//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Enketo has become much faster over the past few weeks (some people even say it is now faster than a peregrine falcon!).&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2013/03/benchmarks.png&quot; alt=&quot;enketo benchmarks chart&quot; /&gt;There are two sides to enketo’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, there is server performance, which is mostly concerned with transforming the underlying (XForm) format to a HTML form that works in a browser. For the average form this happens very quickly, usually within a second. However, we noticed that for very long forms with translations this transformation can take several minutes. For this reason we added a caching mechanism in January that reduced the ‘serving time’ to virtually zero for all launched forms after they have been loaded once (form previews can still take very long as these are not cached). This improvement is not reflected in the graph above as it was already in place before the benchmarks were created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, there is client performance. This concerns everything that has to be done to display the form correctly in your browser (after it has been served by the server). In enketo, all the form logic is handled by the browser, so client performance plays a crucial role in making it all feel snappy. The graph above shows the client-performance improvements of the last few weeks*. All forms now load significantly faster and the average form now appears instantaneously. Of course, the actual loading times vary depending on how powerful the computer/mobile is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is now only one major performance bottleneck remaining for forms with a lot of ‘relevant’ logic (aka skip logic) or calculations. In a few months this bottleneck will be addressed as well, but I hope most of the enketo users won’t even need this with the current blazing speed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*form 5 and form 6 were not even able to load successfully in January, hence the missing bars&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Enketo: Why so awesome?</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-a-unique-survey-app//" />
	  <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-a-unique-survey-app//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been 3 months now since enketo was quietly launched on &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;formhub web site&quot;&gt;formhub.org&lt;/a&gt; and I have had a great time so far at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs&quot; title=&quot;GitHub repositories of modilabs&quot;&gt;Modilabs&lt;/a&gt;. We are getting encouraging feedback from users and have many ideas on how to make enketo even more awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/12/ss1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;enketo screenshot&quot; /&gt;
I started enketo to provide a way to address the lack of modern and efficient IT tools in the developing world. As a former aid worker, I had first-hand experience of this problem and it seemed mostly related to poor Internet connectivity. Enketo was designed to have the benefits of a modern web application but without the ‘always-online’ dependency. This became possible by utilizing new offline-capable web technologies related to HTML 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enketo was initially targeted at aid organizations working in emergencies to conduct collaborative needs assessments. However, during the course of the project its potential in a much wider context became clear. It evolved from a basic app using a custom JSON form format to a powerful application that is able to handle complex forms in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/javarosa/javarosa/wiki/xform-jr-compat&quot; title=&quot;XForms as supported by JavaRosa&quot;&gt;open-source JavaRosa Xform format&lt;/a&gt;. It is fully compatible with other applications in the JavaRosa ecosystem,  and like &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;formhub web site&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/javarosa/javarosa/wiki/Home&quot; title=&quot;JavaRosa wiki&quot;&gt;JavaRosa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org&quot; title=&quot;OpenDataKit web site&quot;&gt;ODK&lt;/a&gt;, enketo is 100% free and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MartijnR/enketo&quot;&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enketo is a lightweight app that does one thing – data entry – and tries to do that well. It forms one component of a system that together with form building, data aggregation and data analysis tools provides a complete solution to collect, create and share information. The unique combination of key features that enketo offers are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;low technical requirements&lt;/strong&gt; - It only requires a modern browser to run. It can therefore be deployed by users very quickly on pretty much any laptop or desktop and is becoming quite usable on mobile devices as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;print-friendly forms&lt;/strong&gt; - This facilitates old-school data collection (and modern data entry) with pen and paper without the need to maintain a separate print-version of the form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;offline-capable&lt;/strong&gt; - Forms in enketo open without an Internet connection (after a form has been opened once online, a copy is kept inside the browser). A user can just bookmark a form and from then onwards access it whether offline or online. Enketo also safely stores entered data in the browser and uploads records automatically (e.g. to &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;formhub web site&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt;) when the user is connected to the Internet. Only after a successful upload, the data is deleted from the browser. A user can safely close the browser or laptop and work for weeks (or months) without an Internet connection!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;open, free and compatible&lt;/strong&gt; - Due to its openness and compatibility with a popular standard, it is relatively easy to integrate enketo into existing OpenRosa systems such as was done in &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;formhub web site&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the next few months users can expect improvements in the general user interface, print-friendliness, mobile-friendliness and support for authentication. Moreover, in my spare time, I’m working on the launch of enketo as a standalone app that will be hosted on enketo.org.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Enketo is now open source and will be used in formhub!</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-is-now-open-source-and-will-be-used-in-formhub//" />
	  <updated>2012-09-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/enketo-is-now-open-source-and-will-be-used-in-formhub//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce that the enketo source code has now been released under an open source license on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MartijnR/enketo&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and that enketo has received a great boost!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/09/Screen-Shot-2012-09-12-at-10.06.25-AM-300x220.png&quot; alt=&quot;formhub web site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve joined the &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt; team at Modilabs (Columbia University) and will continue working on enketo for them in the next few months. This means enketo (or enketo-powered tools) will become a reality and will benefit greatly from lots of new ideas of, and collaboration with, the very talented Modilabs team. In the past 2 weeks the new direction and look has started to take shape and it is going to be very cool. The active repository for enketo in the near future will be &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/enketo&quot;&gt;this fork&lt;/a&gt;. The best source for news on enketo will probably become the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.formhub.org/&quot;&gt;formhub blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>JavaScript XPath Evaluator for OpenRosa/JavaRosa</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/javascript-xpath-evaluator//" />
	  <updated>2012-08-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/javascript-xpath-evaluator//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After finding a suitable &lt;a href=&quot;/enketos-new-architecture/&quot; title=&quot;Enketo’s New Architecture&quot;&gt;open-source form format&lt;/a&gt; to use in enketo there was need to properly evaluate the very powerful processing logic it supports. For example, the format allows you to describe how one survey question depends on the answer to an earlier question. This logic is written in a language called &lt;em&gt;XPath&lt;/em&gt; and I therefore needed an &lt;em&gt;XPath Evaluator&lt;/em&gt;. Since enketo is offline-capable this processor would have to work without server interaction inside a browser. This meant I could not use the open-source Java libraries provided by the JavaRosa project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I had high hopes for the (crazy fast) native XPath evaluator built into modern browsers. However, it became apparent that it is not really possible to extend this with custom functions. Moreover, browsers do not all implement XPath in the same way (sigh…). XPath is an extensible language and has been extended with useful functions in JavaRosa, so extensibility was crucial. Eventually, I found an excellent cross-browser open-source project called&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andrejpavlovic/xpathjs&quot; title=&quot;XPathJS on GitHub&quot;&gt; XPathJS &lt;/a&gt;by Andrej Pavlovic (Andrej, thank you for making this available!). I forked his project and simply added the custom functions and the custom (date) datatype that JavaRosa has included in their format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MartijnR/xpathjs_javarosa/&quot; title=&quot;XPathJS_javarosa on GitHub&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/08/Screen-Shot-2012-08-21-at-11.33.20-AM-300x220.png&quot; alt=&quot;xpathjs_javarosa github screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My port is now available on GitHub and is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MartijnR/xpathjs_javarosa/&quot; title=&quot;XPathJS_javarosa on GitHub&quot;&gt;XPathJS_javarosa&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully, this project will contribute to the creation of more JavaRosa clients for the browser and allow the format to be adopted on a wider scale. I think it is a great thing for organizations when they can easily swap different components (data server, data entry client, form builder) of their information management system. The ability to switch to something new when it becomes available and may meet requirements better – and even to do this on a per-survey basis – is a great advantage compared to systems using proprietary formats and communication protocols. On this note, it is worth mentioning that &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;formhub web site&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt; just added a feature to allow survey administrators to &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/06/posting-to-external-site/&quot; title=&quot;formhub blog post on posting data to an external site&quot;&gt;post data to an external site&lt;/a&gt;, which supports this ability to swap and try out new tools. Very cool!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>A new name: enketo</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/new-name-enketo//" />
	  <updated>2012-08-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/new-name-enketo//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have come up with a better name for the offline-capable-and-open-source-form-format-using &lt;a href=&quot;/enkets-new-architecture/&quot; title=&quot;Enketo’s New Architecture&quot;&gt;survey application&lt;/a&gt; with less scope for confusion. Rapaide has now been renamed to: &lt;strong&gt;enketo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“enketo” is Esperanto for survey and matches well with the wide user potential the application has (beyond aid workers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://enketo.org&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/08/elephantdeath-300x228.png&quot; alt=&quot;enketo screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More updates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaRosa engine is working well and supports repeats (fully), translations (all), constraints, branching, triggers, outputs, defaults, media labels (hosted on Aggregate) and appearances (partial).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The focus in August will be on the data entry component (local storage of data and offline launch). Also, the source code for the fork of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://enketo.org&quot;&gt;javascript XPath evaluator&lt;/a&gt; (to which I’ve just added the custom JavaRosa functions and accompanying tests) will be made available on GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;September will be mostly dedicated to finalizing support for the newer parts of the JavaRosa spec (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org/help/form-design/cascading-selects/&quot; title=&quot;Technical article about the new cascading selects in ODK&quot;&gt;cascading selections&lt;/a&gt;) and creating a huge quantity of additional automated tests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October: widgets…. and then in November the alpha launch(?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Quick look at enketo&#8217;s launch area</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/launch-preview//" />
	  <updated>2012-06-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/launch-preview//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I would like to share some screenshots of &lt;a href=&quot;/enkets-new-architecture/&quot; title=&quot;Enketo’s New Architecture&quot;&gt;enketo’s launch area&lt;/a&gt;. This is the component that survey administrators (not the average user) will use to test and launch survey forms (after uploading the XForm file or providing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;formhub web site&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org/use/aggregate/&quot; title=&quot;ODK Aggregate Info&quot;&gt;ODK Aggregate&lt;/a&gt; URL). At the moment I’m using enketo’s launch area to find bugs in the transformation from XML to HTML5 and in the XForm functionality. I’m using its built-in reporting function to find major errors and monitor the instantly-updated data (in XML) whenever input fields change. I should mention that I have not yet started working on fancy form widgets. The appearance and usability of the forms will improve significantly once I reach that stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I would welcome any sample forms that you think might be useful during testing!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/06/Screen-Shot-2012-08-07-at-8.46.46-AM.png&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot showing form media labels&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing form media labels&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/06/Screen-Shot-2012-08-07-at-8.44.28-AM.png&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot showing plain form and information tabs that help with testing.&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing plain form and information tabs that help with testing.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/06/Screen-Shot-2012-08-07-at-8.47.19-AM.png&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot showing data, updated in realtime&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing data, updated in realtime&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/06/Screen-Shot-2012-08-07-at-8.41.40-AM.png&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot showing form upload feature.&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing form upload feature.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/06/Screen-Shot-2012-08-07-at-8.47.57-AM.png&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot showing XML-to-HTML5 transformation report&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing XML-to-HTML5 transformation report&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Edited: the name Rapaide was replaced by enketo]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Enketo&#8217;s New Architecture</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/enkets-new-architecture//" />
	  <updated>2012-05-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/enkets-new-architecture//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a follow up to the&lt;a href=&quot;/an-introduction-to-rapaide/&quot; title=&quot;An Introduction to Rapaide&quot;&gt; introduction of enketo&lt;/a&gt; and my post about the &lt;a href=&quot;/survey-tools/&quot; title=&quot;Survey Tools&quot;&gt;JavaRosa form format&lt;/a&gt;, I would like to explain the new architecture of enketo. Development work is progressing steadily. Most of the hard stuff in transforming the XML forms into HTML5 forms has been completed using the power of XSLT (wow!), PHP and JavaScript. There is a still a lot of work remaining with other aspects of the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those familiair with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org&quot;&gt;Open Data Kit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot; title=&quot;Formhub website&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kobotoolbox.org/&quot;&gt;Kobo Toolbox&lt;/a&gt;, the following (slightly simplified) diagram should clarify how enketo will fit into these systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/05/Enketo-architecture1.png&quot; title=&quot;Enketo architecture&quot; alt=&quot;Enketo Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, enketo will provide a web-based alternative to ODK Collect or Kobo Collect for situations in which ensuring the availability and/or use of Android devices is not feasible or appropriate. It will seamlessly fit into existing systems that use ODK Aggregate. It will of course be able to &lt;a href=&quot;/offline-capable-web-applications/&quot; title=&quot;Offline-Capable Web Applications&quot;&gt;launch and work offline&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;/humanitarian-aid-browsing/&quot; title=&quot;Humanitarian Aid Browsing&quot;&gt;modern browsers&lt;/a&gt; and will therefore be suitable for situations where Internet connectivity is intermittent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch component validates the forms and facilitates user testing  before the forms become available to the enumerators to collect and enter data. A simplified version of this component will be made available in July/August (depending on other engagements) to a limited audience of ODK users. It will allow users to transform and play with their existing JavaRosa forms and hopefully provide me with some useful feedback (send me a message or reply to this post if you’re interested in helping with this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, depending on the need, there could be an integrated enketo build and analysis component and maybe even a (fast PHP) version of a JavaRosa-compliant server to replace ODK Aggregate. Thankfully, this is not a priority as it is great to be able to use the facilities provided by ODK and Kobo (as well as by some other very interesting players such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.formhub.org/2012/04/09/new-insights-from-your-formhub-map/&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt;). I am particularly impressed with the current &lt;a href=&quot;http://build.opendatakit.org&quot; title=&quot;ODK Form Builder&quot;&gt;ODK Form Builder&lt;/a&gt; (tip: you don’t have to sign in to play around with this, just click cancel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Edit: Replaced Rapaide with enketo]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Internet Explorer 10 &#038; Offline Web Apps</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/internet-explorer-10-will-offer-full-support-for-offline-web-applications//" />
	  <updated>2012-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/internet-explorer-10-will-offer-full-support-for-offline-web-applications//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some good news, that I had missed until now: The new version of Internet Explorer (IE 10) will likely finally support a &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh673546(v=vs.85).aspx&quot; title=&quot;link to Microsoft page&quot;&gt;key feature&lt;/a&gt; for launching web applications offline! Naturally this only works if the application was designed to do this. Read more about offline capable web applications&lt;a href=&quot;/offline-capable-web-applications/&quot; title=&quot;Offline-Capable Web Applications&quot;&gt; this previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/03/Screen-Shot-2012-03-01-at-11.56.43-AM.png&quot; title=&quot;Screen Shot 2012-03-01 at 11.56.43 AM&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Internet Explorer 10 will only run on Windows 7 and Windows 8, so for the foreseeable future that will still exclude most of the field workers in developing countries from using offline-capable web applications unless they upgrade to a &lt;a href=&quot;/humanitarian-aid-browsing/&quot; title=&quot;Humanitarian Aid Browsing&quot;&gt;non-Microsoft browser&lt;/a&gt;. Still, IE10′s support is a decent step forward for the ‘offline web’!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Edit: when testing &lt;a href=&quot;/an-introduction-to-enketo/&quot; title=&quot;An Introduction to Rapaide&quot;&gt;Enketo&lt;/a&gt;, the offline launch does not appear to work correctly yet in the current preview version of IE10]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Survey Tools</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/survey-tools//" />
	  <updated>2012-02-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/survey-tools//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the process to re-think the further development of &lt;a href=&quot;../an-introduction-to-rapaide/&quot; title=&quot;An Introduction to Rapaide&quot;&gt;Enketo&lt;/a&gt;, I have been browsing ‘the tubes’ to look at other available tools and standards to link with or to adopt. I must say, it has been very enlightening! There are some active and very supportive communities out there that are working on cutting-edge tools to collect data in developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org&quot; title=&quot;OpenDataKit website&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/02/odk_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Open Data Kit logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org&quot; title=&quot;OpenDataKit website&quot;&gt;Open Data Kit (ODK)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kobotoolbox.org/&quot;&gt;Kobo Toolbox&lt;/a&gt; (the latter is a spin-off of the former) are very interesting open-source toolkits. Both kits are using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dimagi.com/javarosa/&quot; title=&quot;JavaRosa description on Dimagi web site&quot;&gt;JavaRosa&lt;/a&gt; flavour of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XForms&quot; title=&quot;XForms description on wikipedia&quot;&gt;XForms&lt;/a&gt; standard. The fact that the tools are open-source and are using a standard means their tools are interchangeable (or at least could be). There are other tools out there that are considering adopting this standard (Voozanoo e.g.), which I take as a very good sign that helps to confirm that this is the standard Enketo should incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kobotoolbox.org&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/02/kobotoolbox_logo-300x71.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kobo Toolbox logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Both ODK and Kobo toolkits include the use of Android devices for the actual collection of data in the field. I can think of many contexts and types of surveys where this would be a very appropriate choice. For the key target user group of Enketo – aid workers conducting needs assessments in an emergency – this may be less feasible. For this group, I think an approach using paper and pen in the field and a browser on any old laptop for efficient data entry will remain a more practical solution for the data collection and entry components of the toolkits (I will go into this a bit further in a future post). This means that Enketo could potentially serve as a complementary component for these great toolkits. It would seem perfect!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to learn more about the tools and the future plans of these interesting projects in the next few weeks to be able to make some decisions on how to proceed with Enketo.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>An Introduction to enketo</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/an-introduction-to-enketo//" />
	  <updated>2012-01-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/an-introduction-to-enketo//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;[updated: 1 Feb 2012]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/01/Screen-Shot-2012-01-02-at-4.52.53-PM-300x209.png&quot; title=&quot;Rapaide &quot; alt=&quot;screenshot of Rapaide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of last year, I spent a few months developing a survey application specifically meant for collaborative humanitarian needs assessments, e.g. amongst &lt;a href=&quot;http://oneresponse.info/COORDINATION/CLUSTERAPPROACH/Pages/Cluster&quot;&gt;Clusters&lt;/a&gt;. The application is named ‘Rapaide’ – a combination of &lt;em&gt;Rapide&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Aide&lt;/em&gt; enketo. Its key advantage and the reason I decided to develop this offline-capable application is &lt;strong&gt;its speed&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows for very quick deployment, efficient data entry, fast collation of data from different partners and realtime analysis. Users do not require fancy devices to enter data – a laptop or desktop with a modern browser will suffice (so better not Internet Explorer – you may notice that I mention that a lot…). The development work on this app will soon resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/01/Screen-Shot-2012-01-02-at-4.56.37-PM-300x209.png&quot; title=&quot;Rapaide Local Data&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot of Rapaide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project initially aimed to include 3 main components: an online form designer, an offline-capable data entry component and an online data analysis component. An all-in-one solution seemed the best at the time. However, I am currently re-evaluating this design. It may be better to focus on what distinguishes enketo from all the survey applications that are out there: &lt;strong&gt;its ability to enter data in a browser without an Internet connection&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. being able to launch offline and able to save data offline, see &lt;a href=&quot;../offline-capable-web-applications/&quot;&gt;this earlier post)&lt;/a&gt;. I am considering focusing on completing the data entry application and relying on existing services to design surveys and analyse data. This has the following advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/01/Screen-Shot-2012-01-02-at-4.57.34-PM-300x198.png&quot; title=&quot;Rapaide Analysis 1&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot of Rapaide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rarely is an application good at everything. It may be better to focus on one aspect and try to do this very well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a wide range of advanced data analysis tools available. Survey administrators using enketo will now be able to pick the most suitable for their purpose. The most appropriate tool may vary depending on the type of survey and available skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The survey application could complement existing systems by replacing only the data entry component without replacing a whole system. For example, it could be deployed in an existing system that currently utilizes a data entry method or device that is not appropriate in a primary emergency or uses a cumbersome technology to deal with problematic Internet access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application can stay very lean, which means fewer bugs, less maintenance, less testing and generally faster development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So far this has been a hobby but a potential way to monetize the application in the future could be to offer custom ‘hand-coded’ reports for fixed survey designs which would provide better reports than a flexible user-configured reporting tool could.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since I am developing the application by myself and there are limits to my available time, this leaner application could launch in 2012 instead of 2013, 2014….&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The main features I am currently considering to include are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to import a form (design) created with a third-party tool (ideally one using a standard)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to test launch a survey before launching it officially&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to enter survey data on any device with a modern browser, online and offline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automatic uploading and collating of finalized data when the device is online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to view the collated data and export this as a spreadsheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to link to an external web page on which reports are published&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2012/01/Screen-Shot-2012-01-02-at-4.57.43-PM-300x198.png&quot; title=&quot;Rapaide Analysis 2&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot of Rapaide&quot; /&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Development will re-start some time in February or March, depending on my other engagements. Data entry, collation and export (#3, #4 and #5) are mostly functioning at the moment (pre-alpha) with a fixed form. If you work for an international humanitarian aid agency and are interested in a demo, just let me know and I would be happy to set something up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Edit: Rapaide was replaced with enketo]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Building a manifest with PHP</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/building-a-manifest-with-php//" />
	  <updated>2011-12-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/building-a-manifest-with-php//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Warning: this is a technical post (an exception)…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in a &lt;a href=&quot;/offline-capable-web-applications/&quot;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; offline-capable web application technology has the potential to offer exciting opportunities for aid workers once suitable apps become available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For application developers, creating an offline-capable web application starts by ordering the browser to create a persistent copy of the application in its Application Cache. This is done using a manifest file with a specific format that contains a list of the required offline resources (files) plus a few other things. From experience, I can share that creating and updating such a manifest by hand when a developing a web application is a thoroughly frustrating exercise due to the difficulty to troubleshoot the many problems that can, and will, arise. Moreover, it is inconvenient to manually update the version number each time the code has changed. Ideally this should all be automated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gearsblog.blogspot.com/2011/03/stopping-gears.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2011/12/Manifest_builder-300x190.png&quot; alt=&quot;GitHub screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built a controller for the CodeIgniter (PHP) framework that does this. It dynamically creates a manifest and (usually) is able to tell when the application has changed by creating a hash of the resource content. If the hash changes (the ‘version number’ changes) the browser will refresh its Application Cache by downloading a new version of the application the next time it is online. It also includes a method to generate a Gears-formatted manifest (actually obsolete now, because &lt;a href=&quot;http://gearsblog.blogspot.com/2011/03/stopping-gears.html&quot;&gt;Gears has sadly been deprecated&lt;/a&gt;, before the remaining minority of Internet Explorer users finally switched to a &lt;a href=&quot;/humanitarian-aid-browsing/&quot;&gt;better browser&lt;/a&gt;). The Manifest Builder has greatly simplified the development of the offline-capable survey application I am working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Manifest Builder has been open-sourced (my first contribution!) and is available for download on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MartijnR/Manifest-Builder&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Aid Web Solutions is back</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/aid-web-solutions-is-back//" />
	  <updated>2011-12-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/aid-web-solutions-is-back//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a 10 month break due to a consultancy for UNHCR (and a partial basement renovation), work on Aid Web Solutions projects is now slowly re-starting again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I moved the &lt;a href=&quot;http://aidwebsolutions.com&quot; title=&quot;Aid Web Solutions site&quot;&gt;site&lt;/a&gt; and this blog from Concrete5 to WordPress and used a fresh design. This time I went for a commercial off-the-shelf theme (and hacked it) to save time. WordPress is impressive so far and seems suitable for non-blog sites as well. I still like the simplicity of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.concrete5.org&quot; title=&quot;Concrete5 CMS site&quot;&gt;Concrete5&lt;/a&gt;, but it had some limitations for my requirements. Moreover, I enjoyed the opportunity to learn how to work with a (for me) new CMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More about the 2 real web development projects soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Offline-Capable Web Applications</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/offline-capable-web-applications//" />
	  <updated>2011-04-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/offline-capable-web-applications//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2011/04/HTML5_badge.png&quot; title=&quot;HTML5 badge&quot; alt=&quot;HTML5 badge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional web applications are loaded from the server each time a users visits its web address in a web browser. Any user-submitted data has to be transmitted to the server in order to be stored. Without an Internet connection the application will not be able to launch and if an application was launched online but the internet connection is interrupted, it is no longer capable of storing or retrieving data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is meant with offline-capable?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A web application can be called offline-capable if it can be launched without an Internet connection and maintains its (core) functionality whilst offline. Generally, two different modern technologies are used to create offline-capable applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2011/04/Screen-Shot-2011-12-10-at-1.57.33-PM.png&quot; title=&quot;HTML5 Offline Storage icon&quot; alt=&quot;HTML5 Offline Storage icon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is called the application cache and all it does is store a copy of the application inside the browser. Whenever a user browses to the application this local copy is loaded without any interaction with the server. This is therefore superfast! After the application has launched, the browser will check at regular intervals if a newer version of the application is available and if so will download it automatically. The next time you load the application (or refresh your browser) the new version will be loaded. If there is no Internet connection there is no problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second technology allows the storage of data in the browser itself. This data is ‘persistent’ which means. it will still be there after you close the window, browser or shut down your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What do I need to install to use these technologies?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great thing about these technologies is that they are Web Standards (related to HTML5) and should therefore work in any browser out-of-the-box without the need for plugins. All popular browsers support both technologies now except Internet Explorer (no application cache). However, the application needs to be designed to be offline-capable. It is not something that can be added-on to an existing application by a user. So all you need to do when you find an offline-capable web application is use a &lt;a href=&quot;/humanitarian-aid-browsing/&quot; title=&quot;Humanitarian Aid Browsing&quot;&gt;modern browser.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What does this have to do with Humanitarian Aid?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These offline web technologies were specifically meant to be used on mobile phones, because Internet connections are generally less reliable on phones. However, I see a fantastic opportunity for humanitarian aid contexts where Internet connections often exist but are expensive or unreliable. No alternative could match the advantages of offline-capable web applications in collaborative data collection in an emergency. More about that in a future post!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Google Apps in Emergencies</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/google-apps-in-emergencies//" />
	  <updated>2010-12-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/google-apps-in-emergencies//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Google provides a free suite of applications called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/apps/intl/en/group/index.html&quot; title=&quot;Google Apps web site&quot;&gt;Google Apps&lt;/a&gt; (paid licenses with support and additional features are also available with discounts for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/apps/intl/en/nonprofit/index.html&quot; title=&quot;Google Apps for Non-Profits web site&quot;&gt;US-based non-profits&lt;/a&gt;). The applications include GMail, Google Docs, Google Calendar, Picasa and many others by Google and by third parties through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/enterprise/marketplace/&quot; title=&quot;Google Apps Marketplace&quot;&gt;Google Apps Marketplace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/apps/intl/en/business/index.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2010/12/Google-Apps-logo-150x150.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Apps Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Apps is an interesting option for Humanitarian Aid organizations that quickly need to set up a field office in an emergency (as well as for HQ), despite the fact that web applications require an Internet connection (some work offline though, but more about that later  and in future posts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take for example the requirement for a field office to use email and set up email accounts. I’ve often seen organizations use HQ-managed solutions or cumbersome local Outlook Exchange servers. Local Windows servers require skills that may not be to easy to find (or import) in an emergency and HQ-managed solutions do not offer enough control for field offices to quickly create a new email account or troubleshoot issues. Many aid workers have to resort to using personal email accounts which causes problems when those people leave as there is no easily searchable email history. Google Apps offers the familiar web interface of GMail and an easy way to centrally manage the email capability of a field office (share contacts, set up groups, add users, add aliases to accounts, built-in IM, store and search email, etc.).  The only requirements are a domain name and a person with basic software skills. The ‘enterprise email’ capability and speed of setup are the key reasons to recommend Google Apps for humanitarian field offices that have a reasonable access to the Internet. The only real disadvantage over a local Microsoft Exchange Server (or similar solution) is that sending internal emails and receiving emails that are cc-ed to several people inside the same field office require more Internet traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a wealth of additional benefits to using Google Apps in an emergency. For example Google Calendar facilitates the scheduling of meetings, sharing of each others schedules, and reserving shared resources (think for example about satellite phones, BGANs and cameras to take along on field trips). Google Docs is a great way to collaborate on the writing of documents such as proposals and can be combined with a third party application to automatically synchronize files with a local folder so they can be accessed and edited without an Internet connection (eg &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insynchq.com/&quot; title=&quot;InSync&quot;&gt;InSync&lt;/a&gt;). Picasa is an excellent tool for maintaining a photo database and supports features such a geo-tagging and basic editing. Moreover, uploaded photos can be instantly made available to fundraising colleagues in HQ. There are tons of other tools that could be (carefully) selected and made available to Google Apps users in the field office. They vary from advanced &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/enterprise/marketplace/search?categoryId=6&amp;amp;orderBy=rating&quot; title=&quot;Project Management tools in Google Apps Marketplace&quot;&gt;Project Management tools&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/enterprise/marketplace/search?categoryId=0&amp;amp;orderBy=rating&quot; title=&quot;Accounting &amp;amp; Finance tools in Google Apps Marketplace&quot;&gt;Accounting&lt;/a&gt;. All tools are accessible with the same user account and can be centrally managed by the administrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the Google Apps tools can be launched (and maintain their functionality) when the user is offline. This feature is not specific to Google Apps but Google is definitely on the forefront of introducing this state-of-the-art offline web application technology. This is an area I will write about much more in future posts as is it the specialty of Aid Web Solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	 
	<entry>
	  <title>Humanitarian Aid Browsing</title>
	  <link href="http://blog.enketo.org/humanitarian-aid-browsing//" />
	  <updated>2010-10-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
	  <id>http://blog.enketo.org/humanitarian-aid-browsing//</id>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seems appropriate to kick off a blog about web applications for the humanitarian aid community with a post on browsers. Your web experience, including the speed, can be greatly affected by the brand and version of browser you are using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opera.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2010/10/Opera-128.png&quot; title=&quot;Opera logo&quot; alt=&quot;Opera logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/safari/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2010/10/browser-128x128.png&quot; title=&quot;Safari logo&quot; alt=&quot;Safari logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mozilla.org/firefox/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2010/10/Firefox-128.png&quot; title=&quot;Firefox logo&quot; alt=&quot;Firefox logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/chrome/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2010/10/Chrome-128.png&quot; title=&quot;Chrome logo&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/internet-explorer/download-ie&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../files/2010/10/IE-128.png&quot; title=&quot;Internet Explorer logo&quot; alt=&quot;Internet Explorer logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the web is built around agreed standards, there are (sadly) differences in how these standards are implemented in browsers. Moreover, some browser manufacturers are more pro-active in adopting future standards that are almost-but-not-quite final. In the best case, using a sub-standard browser will result in web pages that do not look exactly the way they were meant to look but are readable. In the worst case, web pages become unreadable or applications do not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two most exciting new developments in the world of browsers are two updated web languages: HTML 5 and CSS 3. With these new versions and related technologies, the web is bound to improve for users as well as for developers. Safari and Chrome browsers already provide excellent support for these new standards. Opera provides good support as well and Firefox will catch up when version 4 is released in early 2011. The perennial disappointment is Internet Explorer (IE). Even the much-hyped forthcoming version 9 (November 2010) will lag far behind the competition. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aidwebsolutions.com/&quot; title=&quot;Aid Web Solutions&quot;&gt;Aid Web Solutions&lt;/a&gt; site was developed using HTML 5 and CSS 3. It looks much better in Chrome, Safari and Opera than it does in Internet Explorer. Creating alternative browser-specific solutions to cope with IE’s deficiencies requires a lot of code (=expensive) and it could make the page slower to load. It is likely that in the near future more developers and clients will accept a degraded experience for users with sub-standard browsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most web applications, an important factor is the speed in which operations can be performed on the local computer using the so-called &lt;em&gt;JavaScript engine &lt;/em&gt;that is built into the browser. This is particularly important for applications that try to minimize the amount of server interaction to create a responsive application.&lt;strong&gt; That is exactly the kind of web application that could be perfectly suitable for a humanitarian aid context with slow and intermittent Internet connections.&lt;/strong&gt; JavaScript engines are getting faster with each new browser version and therefore provide an extra incentive to always update your browser to the latest version. The browser with the slowest JavaScript engine is of course…..Internet Explorer (except for displaying certain kinds of video). See &lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2010/06/safari-5-tested-chrome-opera-still-have-javascript-edge.ars&quot; title=&quot;Browser JavaScript Engine Benchmarks&quot;&gt;these benchmark tests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poor (or expensive) Internet connections in emergencies may be a constraint for downloading a different browser or a newer version in the field. It could definitely be worthwhile to do this centrally (regularly) and distribute the installation file amongst employees, the old-fashioned way (e.g via usb flash drives or a local network). For Windows,  Chrome would be the preferred choice at the moment because of its speed, support of the latest (useful) technologies and accurate rendering of text.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>